All right, so in this video, we are going
to be discussing controlling procurement.
This refers to the PIMBock Guide process
called Control Procurement, as we're going
to be monitoring and controlling the
procurement process.
Okay, now, before we start talking
specifically about monitoring,
control, procurement,
let's just do a quick review
of what monitoring
controlling actually refers to.
Remember, monitoring controlling is
comparing your actual results with your plan.
That's what we're doing.
We have our actual results.
We have our plan.
That's what we should deliver.
This is what we actually delivered.
Where's a discrepancy?
Why is there a discrepancy?
And that's exactly what we're doing here,
but from the other way around,
right, from the procurement process.
In other words, we are the customer.
The vendor is performing the work.
So as the vendor is performing
the work, we are trying to
determine, are they doing the
work that's supposed to be doing?
This is what they should be delivering.
this is what they're actually delivering.
So, we are monitoring their adherence to
the contract.
Are they doing what they're supposed to be
doing?
And we're trying to quantify their ability
to actually perform the work.
How well are they performing?
What's their cost performance index?
What's their schedule performance index?
Are they working efficiently?
Or, you know, are they working really
inefficiently?
And we're wondering why we hired these
people.
So again, as a very simple
example, you're doing some
work in your house, you're
doing some remodeling work.
Well, as the vendor is performing the
work, as a customer, what are you doing?
You're walking around seeing how they're
progressing.
Are they putting the
right walls in the right
places, the right cabinets
against the right walls?
Are they painting the right walls in the
right color and so on and so forth?
You're seeing how they are progressing.
You're monitoring their adherence to the
contract.
Are they doing what they're supposed to be
doing?
And then plus, you're quantifying their
ability.
to perform the work.
How efficiently are they performing?
They're painting your room.
Are they being nice and clean?
Right.
They're nice, clean paint, even paint
everywhere.
Or are they just being really sloppy?
And there's paint splashes everywhere on
the floor, on the carpet, on the,
and the windows.
So, again, that's something you or the
customer are going to be doing.
So that is what monitoring
controlling procurement
refers to, or the process is
called control procurement.
That's what this is referring to.
So it's basically, as it says here,
the first bullet point, managing the
procurement performance, managing the
performance of your vendor.
So controlling, you can only
start really monitoring controlling
the performance of the vendor
once the contract is signed.
Once they've signed the contract,
then they start performing the work.
So you're identifying then the
relationship or managing their
relationship, identifying success and
failures of the procurement relationship.
Success and fail is of the procurement
process.
Again, what's going well, what's going
right?
Are they doing what they're supposed to be
doing?
Right.
And quantifying their ability to actually
perform the work.
Now, the way you are going to be
monitoring control of the work is also
going to differ slightly based on what
kind of contract you have.
So, for example, then, in a fixed price
contract, in a fixed price contract,
in a fixed price contract, you don't
really care about the cost.
You want the work to be done regardless of
what it's going to cost the seller.
Remember, in a fixed price contract, the
seller has all of the
risk of the contract.
So it's a seller that is controlling all
of the cost.
You as a buyer don't care
about what the cost is, but
the seller is the one that's
controlling all the cost.
And since the seller is controlling all of
the cost, you have to be careful that they
are actually delivering again what they're
supposed to be delivering.
There's a lot of bait and switch that can
go on in a fixed price contract.
So what you want to do then
as a customer, as a project
manager, ensure the work is
being performed as contracted.
They're not taking any shortcuts.
They're doing all the work that's supposed
to be doing.
They're delivering what they're supposed
to be delivering.
So as a very simple example, again, you're
doing some remodeling work in your house.
They promised just one grading quality of,
say, you know, kitchen cabinets,
and they're actually
delivering a much poorer
grading quality of
kitchen cabinets, right?
Or they're putting up drywall.
They promised one thickness of drywall,
but now they're actually delivering,
you know, a much cheaper drywall,
like a much thinner drywall.
So that's a bait and switch.
They're not delivering what they actually,
what they promised.
Now, in a cost reimbursable contract,
if it's a cost reimburseable contract.
Now, you as a buyer, you have all of the
risk of the contract, right?
You are the one therefore that is
controlling all of the cost.
You need to control the cost.
So then you are especially monitoring the
seller's cost in this case.
And are they bringing in tons and tons of
raw materials that you don't really need?
Are they bringing in resources that are
not adding value?
They're bringing in just a, you know,
bringing in a whole bunch of team members
that you're paying for, but they're not
really doing anything.
A lot of team members are just hanging
around and they're not really being
productive yet you're still paying for
their time.
And they're bringing a
whole bunch of raw materials,
additional raw materials
that's not really needed.
But you're the one that's paying for them
because the seller doesn't
care what the cost is.
You're the one that's reimbursing them for
the cost.
So in this case, in a
cost Reimversible you
really have to monitor the seller's costs.
Also in cost to reimburseable you're going
to be getting loads of invoices and
receipts, right, for raw material that
they've purchased, they'll be sending you
receipts and invoices for,
you know, other team members
work that the subcontractors
work that they hired.
So they'll be sending you all these
invoices, all these receipts, well,
you also want to make sure that the
invoices and receipts they sent you
actually relate to your project and not to
another project that they're working on.
And again, that can happen as well.
And even, I mean, inadvertently,
I'm not saying that vendors do this on
purpose, but inadvertently,
they could be charging new raw
materials that they're using
actually for a different project.
They might be working on two or three
different projects at the same time.
Right?
So that's something you have to watch out
for as well.
And also ensure that the
resources they're actually
bringing in the resources
that they had contracted for.
So for example, do they
really need to bring in senior
consultants when journey
consultants can do the job just as well?
Do you really need a
managing consultant to do just
some basic work that a
junior consultant can do?
So instead of charging for a managing
consultant, you can pay
for a junior consultant.
This is a very simple example.
If it's a time and material contract,
exactly the same as the cost reimbursable,
right, same considerations that we talked
about in cost of reimburseable just now
would apply to time and material,
right, but in addition, also making sure
that the schedule is not being padded,
right?
They're not extending the schedule,
not padding the schedule, because
remember, you are paying them for their
time.
Each unit of time has a profit built into
it.
So they have an incentive to, you know,
extend the timeline.
They have an incentive to take longer to
perform the work.
So they don't have an incentive to work
efficiently.
So what you're looking at is their
productive time.
So if they're charging
you, say, for 45 hours this
week, well, did they actually
do 45 hours worth of work?
Or did they really do 30 hours worth of
work?
And the rest of the time, they're just
hanging around, drinking coffee,
going out for breaks, and they're charging
you for the time.
So these are all different
considerations you're going to be
making when you are monitoring
controlling the vendor's work.
Now those were for individual types of
contracts, but overall, for all of
procurement, overall, your responsibilities
are going to include the following.
So as you're monitoring controlling the
work of the vendor, right, you're going to
be doing a performance review, quantifying
the seller's ability to actually perform.
well are they performing.
Again, you know, you're walking around
seeing how they're doing the work,
testing the work, which goes to the next
bullet point here, regular inspection.
Regular inspection.
Inspection means testing.
Right.
So you are testing the work that they're
doing.
If you're up and if they're
doing some work in the house,
you're walking around
seeing how they're progressing.
Right, if you've hired them to develop a
website for you, for example, right,
you're going in there seeing how
they're developing the website,
you're testing the website to
make sure it's doing what it's
supposed to be doing
or any computer software.
So quantifying the seller's ability to
perform the work, monitoring their
adherence to the
contract, are they actually
delivering what they were
supposed to be delivering?
Plus, at the same time
throughout the project,
throughout the procurement,
performance reporting.
So performance reporting such as EVM,
earned value management, right?
All those earned value calculations that
we talked about in the cost management
section, you'll be performing that as
well.
Are we ahead of schedule, behind schedule,
over budget, under budget, what's our CPI,
SPI, and so and so forth.
And then plus part of
performance reporting also
is reporting back to
your senior stakeholders.
Your senior stakeholders will also need a
status of your of your procurement,
right?
So you're going to be reporting back to
them as well.
If there's any changes
that need to be done,
right, you have a change
control process in place.
Right.
So on top of your regular
change control process, this
time you may have a contract
change control process.
Right.
So in this case, a contract change control
process then is going to be basically
making sure you're controlling all changes
to the contract.
If there's any changes to the contract.
So what are the procedures for that?
You're making sure
you're following all of those
procedures regarding
contract change control.
Now contract change
control is generally going to be
a little more complex than
integrated change control.
Integrated change control is internal,
right, for internal within the project.
Now you've got vendors involved, so
you have a contract change control, right?
And so we're going to
be covering, you know,
contract change control
in a separate video as well.
And then claims administration,
in case there's a dispute.
You'll be going through the claims
administration process.
And then procurement audit.
Now, if you ever come across system
procurement audit.
A procurement audit was
considered another tool
and technique, a tool and
technique of procurement.
Just like any audit, it is a structured
review of the entire process.
In this case, a structured review of the
entire procurement process, right,
right from the beginning, all the way,
so right from the beginning from the RFI
and RFP stage, right, right from the
beginning all the way up until,
you know, up until the end, up until the
closing, right?
So it's a structured review of the entire
procurement process.
All right, so these were just
some of the considerations
to make then regarding
control procurement.